Guide to the Northern Virginia Civil War images collection, 1853-1914
George Mason University Libraries
- Northern Virginia Civil War images collection
  - [Rappahannock River] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 41)
    - Pontoon Bridges over the Rappahannock, Built for Reynold's Corps, May 16, 1863, 14.5A; Wood Engraving; 4 3/4" x 13 3/4"
    - Pontoon Bridges for General Sedgwick's Corps to Cross, May 16, 1863, 14.5B; Wood Engraving; 4 1/2" x 13 3/4"
    - A Topographical Map of Eastern Virginia from "Fredericksburg" to Richmond," Taken from Tracings (Now in the Possession of the Government) of the Original Railroad Surveys of This Portion of the State, Comprising the Topography for Six Miles on Each Side of the Track. This is the Only Reliable Map of This Portion of the State Ever Made May 16, 1863, 14.5C; Wood Engraving; 13 3/4" x 9"
      by Charles Sholt [?]; Harper's Weekly
    - Burnside's Army Crossing the Rappahannock from Falmouth to Fredericksburg, at Midnight, Wednesday. December 10th, 1862, 14.7; Wood Engraving; 9 1/4" x 14"
    - Christmas Day on the Rappahannock in 1862, December 11, 1886, 14.8; Hand colored wood engraving; 14" x 19 3/4"
      by Gilbert Gaul; Harpers Weekly
    - The Army of the Potomac - Capture by Sedgwick's Corps of the Rebel Works on the Rappahannock, near the Railway Bridge, November 28, 1863; 14.9; Wood Engraving
    - Russell's Brigade (First Division Sixth Army Corps) Crossing the Rappahannock in Pontoons to Storm the Rebel Works, May 16, 1863; 14.10; Wood Engraving
    - The Army of the Potomac - View of the Rappahannock Looking toward Falmouth, March 28, 1863, 20.26; Wood Engraving; 7" x 20 1/2"
  - [Rappahannock II] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 42)
    - Volunteer Storming Parties, Taken from the Seventh Michigan and the Nineteenth and Twentieth Massachusetts Regiments, Crossing the Rappahannock, in Advance of the Grand Army, to Drive off the Confederate Sharpshooters Annoying the Pontoniers, December 11th, 1862, 14.6A; Wood Engraving; 14 1/2" x 20"
    - Generals Pleasanton and Bayard, and Colonel Percy Wyndham, Making a Cavalry Reconnaissance near Fredricksburg, VA., 14.6B; Wood Engraving; 8 3/4" x 9"
    - Ponton-Wagons on Their Way from Aquia Creek to the Rappahannock, 14.6C; Wood Engraving; 9 1/2" x 8 3/4"
  - [Roche's Mills] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 43)
    - Camp of the Garibaldi Guards, Colonel D'Utassy, Near Roche's Mills, VA., Potomac River in the Distance, unnumbered; Hand Colored Wood Engraving
  - [Trevilian Station] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 44)
    - Cavalry Battle at Trevilian Station, June 12, 1864, unnumbered; Wood Engraving
      The Confederate Soldier in the Civil War
  - [Vienna] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 45)
    - General Schenck, with Four Companies of the First Ohio Regiment, Surprised and Fired into by a Confederate Masked Battery, near Vienna, VA., June 17th, 1861, 19.1A; Wood Engraving; 9" x 14"
      [same image as 19.2A]
    - The battle of Bull Run, between the Federal Army, Commanded by Major General McDowell, and the Confederate Army, under Generals Johnston and Beauregard, on July 21st, 1861 - Advance of the Federal Troops, 19.1B; Wood Engraving; 9 1/4" x 14"
      [same image as 19.2B]
    - General Schenck, with Four Companies of the First Ohio Regiment, Surprised and Fired into by a Confederate Masked Battery, near Vienna, VA., June 17th, 1861, 19.2A; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 9" x 14"
      The Civil War in the United States [same image as 19.1A]
    - The battle of Bull Run, between the Federal Army, Commanded by Major General McDowell, and the Confederate Army, under Generals Johnston and Beauregard, on July 21st, 1861 - Advance of the Federal Troops, 19.2B; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 9 1/4" x 14"
      The Civil War in the United States [same image as 19.1B]
  - [Virginia] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 46)
    - Grant's Campaign in Virginia - 1. Hancock's 2nd Corps Charging Lee's Right, in Front of Spottsylvania Courthouse, May 12. 2. Rebel Guns Captured in Hancock's Charge, June 11, 1864, unnumbered; Hand Colored Wood Engraving
      By E. Forbes; Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper
    - A. The United States Military Telegraph Line at the Junction of the Alexandria, Loudon and Hampshire R.R. and Aqueduct Road from Georgetown, Alexandria, County, VA, Communicating with the Military Department at Washington, D.C.; B. Reconnoitreing the Shores of the Potomac at Night to Discover the Military Works of the Sucessionists by Means of Professor Grant's Powerful Calcium Light, July 6, 1861, 4.13; Wood Engraving
    - Virginia One Hundred Years Ago, August 19, 1876, 15.1; Wood Engraving; 9 1/4" x 13 1/2"
      by Sol Eytinge; Harper's Weekly
    - General Grant's Campaign in Virginia, June 9, 1864, 15.2; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 13 3/4" x 20 1/4"
    - The Effect of the Rebellion on the Homes in Virginia, December 24, 1864, 15.3; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 13 1/2" x 20 1/4"
      Harper's Weekly [same image as 15.4 in folder 46]
    - The Effect of the Rebellion on the Homes in Virginia, December 24, 1864, 15.4; Wood Engraving; 13 1/2" x 20 1/4"
      Harper's Weekly [same image as 15.3 in folder 46]
    - Our Army Before Richmond - Reconnoissance in Force of the National Troops Under General Hooker and Defeat of the Rebels at Malvern Hills, August 5, August 23, 1862, 15.5; Wood Engraving; 13 1/2" x 20 1/4"
  - [Virginia II] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 47)
    - Manuscript Map of Virginia, West of Washington D.C., [ca. 1861], unnumbered; Hand Drawn; 18" x 23"
  - [Warrenton] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 48)
    - A. Warrenton, Virginia; B. McClellan's Adieux to his Officers at Warrenton, Virginia, November 29, 1862, unnumbered; Wood engraving
      By Mr. Theodore R. Davis; Harper's Weekly
    - The War in America: Warrenton, Virginia, May 30, 1863, 20.7; Hand colored wood engraving; 6 1/2" x 9 1/4"
  - [Washington D.C.] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 49)
    - The Defences at Washington [map], August 8, 1863; unnumbered; Hand Colored Wood Engraving
    - The Operations Near Washington - Scene of the Fight in Front of Fort Stevens, July 12 and 13, August 6, 1864, 5.1; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 9 12" x 14 1/4"
      by E. F. Mullen; Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper
    - The Freshet in the Potomac - The Ice Gorge at the Long Bridge at Washington, D. C., and the Morning of Feb. 5th, February 23, 1867, 5.2A; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 5 1/4" x 14 1/4"
    - The Steamers and Tugs Forcing a Passage through the Ice at Washington, D. C., to Escape Destruction, February 23, 1867, 5.2B; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 4" x 7"
    - Destruction of Vessels and Piers at Georgetown, D. C., by the Ice During the Great Freshet of February 5th, February 23, 1867, 5.2C; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 4" x 7"
    - "Sharpshooting" - Trial of Skill of Berdan's Riflemen, Before General McClellan and Staff, Near Washington, Friday, September 20, October 5, 1861, 5.4; Hand Colored Wood Engraving
    - Views of the Great Aqueduct, Washington, District of Columbia, May 14, 1864, 5.5; Hand Colored Wood Engraving; 9 1/4" x 13 3/4"
    - Experimental Practice in Pontoning - Constructing Rope Suspension and Rubber Ponton Bridges at Camp Alexander, near Washington, D. C., in Presence of General McClellan and Staff, 5.6; Wood Engraving; 14 1/2" x 19 3/4"
      The Soldier in Our Civil War [same image as 5.7 in folder 48]
    - Prince Napoleon Visiting President Lincoln at the White House, Washington, D. C. - Scene on the Balcony during the Performance by the Band, August 17, 1861, 5.6A; Wood Engraving; 9 1/4" x 14"
    - Block-House Erected near Fort Corcoran, Arlington Heights, VA., by the Twenty-Eighth Regiment, N. Y. S. M., August 17, 1861, 5.6B; Wood Engraving; 7 1/4" x 9 1/4"
    - Bewegliche Brucken fur unsere Armee. - Ponton- und Seilbrucker. - Die 300 Fuk lange Ponton-Brucke uber den Anacosta, den ostlichen Arm des potomac, von einer Abtheilung des 15. Regiments New Yorker Freiwilligen, Oberst McLeod Murphy, in zwanzig Minuten gebaut, 5.7; Wood Engraving; 14 1/4" x 19 3/4"
      Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper [German Language Edition][same image as 5.6 in folder 48]
    - Washington D.C. - Early Morning At the Centre Market, November 13, 1886, 5.8; Hand Colored Wood Engraving
    - Grand Corral or Horse Depot Near Washington D.C. for the Requirements of the Army of the Potomac (Calvary depot and Corcoran's private art building in Washington D.C.), 5.9; Hand Colored Wood Engraving
    - Washington Fish Hatcheries, July 21, 1888, 5.10; Hand Colored Wood Engraving
      Harper's Weekly (supplement)
    - Washington D.C. - The Inauguration of President Hayes, March 5th - The Ovation in the Evening at the White House, March 24, 1877, 5.11; Hand Colored Wood Engraving
    - An Artist's Rambles in Washington - No. 5: Scene on an Alexandria Ferry Boat Looking Toward the Capitol, April 19, 1884, 5.12; Hand Colored Wood Engraving
    - Fort Ward, 5.13
      By Gen. Barnard; Defenses of Washington
    - Battery Reno, Fort Reno, 5.14
    - View of Washington From Arlington Heights, 5.14; Wood Engraving
      Cassell's Illustrated History of England
  - [White Plains] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 50)
    - Crossing the Manassas Gap Railroad, and the Alexandria and Warrington Turnpike, at White Plains - Arrival of Reinforcements for Beauregard, at the Camp of the Tiger Zouaves, of Louisiana, September 28, 1861, 20.17; Wood Engraving; 9 1/4" x 13 3/4"
  - [White Springs] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 51)
    - General Beauregard's Camp of Confederate Troops at White Springs, Virginia, near the Manassas Gap Railroad, July 13, 1861, 20.2; Wood Engraving; 7" x 13 3/4"
  - [Yellow Tavern] (Oversize MC Cage, Folder 52)
    - The War in Virginia - Sheridan's Great Battle with J. E. B. Stuart at Yellow Tavern, May 11th, 1864 - The Confederate Raider's Last Fight, 20.29; Wood Engraving; 13 1/2" x 20 1/4"
    - The Siege of Petersburg, VA. - Charge of the Second Division, Ninth Army Corps, into the Crater, July 30th, 1864, 20.29; Wood Engraving; 9 1/4" x 14"